Based on and inspired by the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi, this series
Inspiriert von den Lehren Shri Mataji Nirmala Devis,
aims to explore the evolutionary relationship between two interconnected domains
beschäftigt sich diese Serie mit der Evolution zweier Ausdrucksformen
expressing human awareness at the gross and subtle levels.
des menschlichen Bewusstseins auf der grob- und feinstofflichen Ebene.
It endeavors to elucidate this complex interplay between the current scientific understanding
Die Serie beleuchtet das komplexe Zusammenspiel
of human neuroanatomy; the autonomic nervous system in particular,
zwischen dem autonomen Nervensystem
and the so-called subtle system as described in the traditional literature on yoga.
und dem feinstofflichen System der traditionellen Yoga-Lehren.
Ultimately, the series tries to bring its viewers along this exploratory journey
Die Zuschauer werden in diese Entdeckungsreise einbezogen,
to experience these relationships through meditation as taught by Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi.
um diese Beziehung durch eine Meditation mit Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi zu erfahren.
Thanks everyone for joining us today.
Danke an alle heutigen Zuschauer.
In our previous episode, we started on an exploration
In der letzten Folge betrachteten wir
into the fascinating intersection of neuroscience and spirituality
die Korrelation von Neurowissenschaft und Spiritualität.
with Dr. Ashish Pradhan, who is a distinguished leader in neurology
Dr. Ashish Pradhan ist als Neurologe und Herz-Kreislauf-Experte
and cardiovascular medicine, renowned for his cutting-edge work
für seine bahnbrechende Arbeit und Führungsrolle
and strategic leadership in patient-centric care.
in der patientenorientierten Pflege anerkannt.
He emphasized the importance of understanding the complexities of the nervous system
Er betont die Bedeutung der Komplexität des Nervensystems
as a foundation for exploring the spiritual aspects of being human.
als Grundlage der Erforschung menschlicher Spiritualität.
Dr. Pradhan also talked to us about the brain's evolutionary journey,
Dr. Pradhan sprach über die Evolution des Gehirns
highlighting the fascinating adaptations that have shaped its structure and function.
und hob die Anpassungen seines Aufbaus und seiner Funktion hervor.
And today we welcome all of you to this second episode of our enlightening series
Heute begrüßen wir Sie zur zweiten Folge unserer Serie
with the esteemed Dr. Ashish Pradhan.
mit dem geschätzten Dr. Ashish Pradhan,
Today we're taking this exploration even deeper.
in der wir unsere Entdeckungen vertiefen.
So get ready for another thought-provoking conversation
Erwarten Sie einen weiteren herausfordernden Dialog
as we continue to bridge the worlds of science and spirituality.
zum Thema Wissenschaft und Spiritualität.
Welcome, Dr. Pradhan.
Willkommen, Dr. Pradhan.
Thank you.
Dankeschön.
Thank you for the kind words, Monikaji.
Danke für die freundlichen Worte, verehrte Monika.
Happy to be back.
Ich freue mich, wieder hier zu sein.
We definitely look forward to learning a lot with you in this yet another episode.
Wir freuen uns ebenfalls, heute wieder viel von Ihnen zu lernen.
So, Dr. Pradhan, like I said, in our previous episode,
Dr. Pradhan – in unserer letzten Folge
we delved into the intricate workings of the human nervous system,
befassten wir uns mit der Komplexität des menschlichen
the autonomic nervous system,
und speziell des autonomen Nervensystems
and their connections to our spiritual experiences.
sowie seinen Zusammenhängen mit unseren spirituellen Erfahrungen.
And you also distinguished between the parasympathetic, the sympathetic,
Sie erklärten den Unterschied zwischen parasympathischem und sympathischem System
and explained how they interact to maintain balance,
sowie ihre Interaktion zur Bewahrung des Gleichgewichts
regulate essential functions.
und der Regulation lebenswichtiger Funktionen.
Today we would like to know how the autonomic nervous system intertwines
Wie ist das autonome Nervensystem
with the concept of the human subtle system that you briefly mentioned,
mit dem menschlichen feinstofflichen System verflochten,
and how they influence our spiritual well-being?
und wie beeinflussen beide Systeme unser spirituelles Wohl?
Sure.
Gerne.
Let's get started right away.
Beginnen wir ohne Umschweife.
It's a slightly complex topic.
Wir versuchen, dieses komplexe Thema
We'll try to understand this as best as we can.
so gut wie möglich zu verstehen.
At the very outset, I would like to once again say
Viele Antworten auf Ihre Fragen
that whatever we discuss in response to your questions,
wurden den Lehren
a lot of that knowledge comes from the teachings of Shri Mataji Nirmala Devi,
Shri Mataji Nirmala Devis entnommen.
the founder of Sahaja Yoga meditation,
Sie gründete Sahaja Yoga.
and intertwined, of course,
Natürlich ist dieses Wissen mit dem verflochten,
with what we know about human anatomy and physiology.
was wir über die menschliche Anatomie und Physiologie wissen.
So let's get started.
Treten wir einen Schritt zurück,
Before we try to understand how the autonomic nervous system and the subtle system
um das Zusammenspiel des autonomen Nervensystems
sort of are correlated or interact, let's take a step back
mit dem feinstofflichen System zu verstehen.
and see what constitutes the subtle system.
Was macht das feinstoffliche System aus?
And from there we can proceed towards our understanding of the autonomic nervous system.
Dann betrachten wir das autonome Nervensystem.
The so-called human subtle system, as you'll see in the animation,
Das menschliche feinstoffliche System
comprises nadis.
besteht aus ‘Nadis’.
Nadis are — it's a Sanskrit word — and it can have multiple meanings.
Dieses Sanskrit-Wort kann mehrere Bedeutungen haben:
It can mean nerves, it can mean channels, it can mean tubes, it can mean blood vessels,
Es kann ‘Nerven’, ‘Kanäle’, ‘Röhren’, ‘Blutgefäße’
it can mean lymphatics, it can mean a whole host of things.
sowie ‘Lymphbahnen’ und viele andere Dinge bezeichnen.
It's almost like one word, or like a noun for a collective,
Es ist fast wie ein Oberbegriff
for a whole host of individual things within the body.
für eine Reihe von Dingen im Körper.
This system was described in detail
Dieses System wurde detailliert
by the Yoga Sutras of Patanjali.
in den ‘Yoga-Sutras’ von Patanjali beschrieben.
This is a very ancient Sanskrit text, and what you have in those texts
Dieser sehr alte Sanskrit-Text
is a description of this subtle anatomy
beschreibt die feinstoffliche Anatomie
or physiology within the human body,
oder Physiologie des menschlichen Körpers
within the human system.
oder des menschlichen Systems.
What the subtle system is actually, if we step even one step further
Das feinstoffliche System
or kind of step behind,
spiegelt eigentlich
is actually a reflection within us of the macrocosm.
den Makrokosmos in uns.
So, what do we mean?
Was ist damit gemeint?
What we have within us is the microcosm.
In uns existiert der Mikrokosmos
What exists outside of us, is the macrocosm.
und außerhalb von uns der Makrokosmos.
And within the macrocosm, if we look at how things function,
Die Funktionen des Makrokosmos
there is a system of balance: light and dark, heavy and light,
zeigen ein Gleichgewicht zwischen hell und dunkel,
dry and wet, fire and ice.
schwer und leicht, trocken und nass, heiß und kalt.
So, those are naturally occurring phenomena that are present in nature.
Das sind natürliche Phänomene.
It has also been described—let's say, what we spiritually or metaphorically refer to
Auch spirituelle oder metaphorische Dinge wurden beschrieben
as yin and yang.
wie etwa Yin und Yang.
Just as there is daylight, there is night; there is the sun, there is the moon;
So wie den Tag, gibt es die Nacht, die Sonne und den Mond,
you have high tide, you have low tide, so on and so forth.
Ebbe und Flut,
You have summer and spring; you have fall and winter.
Frühling, Sommer, Herbst und Winter.
So, in nature we have a balance, and systems which, if overactive,
In der Natur gibt es ein Gleichgewicht, doch überaktive Systeme
can trigger an imbalance.
können ein Ungleichgewicht auslösen.
In other words, if we have too much heat, that isn't good for the system;
Übergroße Hitze ist genauso schlecht für das System
if it's too cold, it isn't good for the system in general.
wie zu große Kälte.
So, ecology, or ecosystems or the universal constants that we see around us
Ökologie, Ökosysteme oder universelle Konstanten unserer Umgebung
is a very good way to begin to get an understanding
geben uns eine sehr gute Vorstellung
of what the human subtle system is about.
vom menschlichen feinstofflichen System.
To slowly start coming
Betrachten wir die Details
into the details and trying to answer the question.
und versuchen, die Frage zu beantworten.
As the human being evolved, or as the Homo sapiens evolved
Als sich der Homo sapiens entwickelte,
as we discussed the last time, the nervous system was an adaptation
war das Nervensystem eine Anpassung
to evolutionary pressures, and those evolutionary pressures
an den evolutionären Druck.
engendered two broad systems of phenomenon
Dieser Druck brachte aus der Perspektive Darwins
from a Darwinian point of view.
zwei große Phänomene hervor:
The first one was the fight or the flight response.
Das erste war die Kampf-oder-Flucht-Reaktion.
The fight or flight response comes into play
Sie kommt ins Spiel,
if there is a threat to the organism in the environment,
wenn eine Bedrohung für den Organismus besteht und
and then it leads to what Darwin called natural selection,
führt zu dem, was Darwin ‘natürliche Selektion’ nannte.
or it brings down pressure upon the system or upon the species to take
Eine Bedrohung übt Druck auf das System oder die Spezies aus,
or to adapt such characteristics that allows it to thrive in the environment.
Eigenschaften für ihr Überleben zu entwickeln.
So either it can overcome the danger,
Ein kleinerer Fisch könnte etwa
a smaller fish could be gobbled
Sinnesorgane, beweglichere Flossen oder schnellere Reflexe entwickeln,
by a bigger fish, so maybe it needs to develop more sensory organs, faster fins, faster reflexes.
um nicht von einem größeren verschlungen zu werden.
Similarly, a gazelle on the Serengeti plains needs to develop responses
Genauso muss eine Gazelle in der Serengeti Reaktionen entwickeln,
to run away from the lion that might pursue it.
um vor den Löwen fliehen zu können.
So, those are flight or flight responses
Kampf- und Fluchtreaktionen sind also
that are part of the evolutionary mechanism.
Teile des evolutionären Mechanismus.
So, the subtle system comprises two aspects to it.
Das feinstoffliche System hat somit
One is a passive aspect, and the other is an active aspect.
einen passiven und einen aktiven Aspekt.
So, we see that even in the cosmos around us, things are dynamic,
Die Dinge im Kosmos sind also manchmal dynamisch,
and sometimes they are passive,
manchmal passiv
both at the same time, and it's not a contradiction.
oder beides gleichzeitig – das ist kein Widerspruch.
The whole system through immutable laws, and we call them the laws of divinity,
Das System insgesamt basiert auf unveränderlichen Gesetzen,
the laws of the Almighty, call it what you will, to each his own,
dies wir auch als göttlich bezeichnen.
but the system works in a state of balance.
Doch das System arbeitet in einem Gleichgewicht.
So, likewise, in the human body, now to start coming back to the point,
Genauso gibt es im menschlichen Körper
we have a system which is the passive system;
ein passives
we have a system which is the active system.
und ein aktives System.
On the left side, so to speak,
Auf der linken Seite
we call it the moon channel, or we call it the Ida Nadi;
haben wir den ‘Mondkanal’ oder ‘Ida Nadi’ und
on the right side, we call it the sun channel, or we call it the Pingala Nadi.
auf der rechten Seite den ‘Sonnenkanal’ oder ‘Pingala Nadi’.
The left side, or the moon channel, is more passive; it allows passivity,
Die linke Seite oder der Mondkanal ist passiver.
but passivity that doesn't mean sloth or lethargy.
Doch Passivität bedeutet nicht automatisch Trägheit oder Lethargie –
It can get into it if it is overactive.
obwohl exzessive Passivität dazu führen kann.
Similarly, on the right side, we have the ability to act,
Entsprechend erlaubt uns die rechte Seite zu handeln
to bring our desires into fruition, but again, if that becomes overactive,
und unsere Wünsche zu verwirklichen.
that becomes a problem too.
Doch Überaktivität wird auch hier problematisch:
We can become: aggressive, overthinking, overplanning, that sort of a thing.
Wir werden aggressiv, denken oder planen zu viel.
So, within the human body, the subtle system has these two components; they are called Nadis,
Das feinstoffliche System hat also diese beiden Nadis.
and that's how it functions.
So funktioniert es.
Now, back to, once again, to the evolutionary component.
Evolutionär gesehen
Within the evolutionary system, as we said, there is a flight or fight pressures,
gibt es einen Druck zu kämpfen oder zu fliehen.
but there is also the need to evolve.
Doch es gibt auch die Notwendigkeit,
The need to evolve into a higher state, both at a physical,
sich zu einem höheren Zustand auf der physischen,
but as well as at a cognitive, or at a nervous system level, or at a neural level.
kognitiven oder neuronalen Ebene zu entwickeln.
And that is how we described during the last session
Das Gehirn entwickelte sich
how the brain evolved in response to some of these pressures.
als Reaktion auf diese Faktoren.
So, likewise, in the subtle system, there is a third component,
Auch das feinstoffliche System beinhaltet eine dritte Komponente:
the so-called Sushumna Nadi, and that is a kind of power
die sogenannte ‘Sushumna Nadi’.
that allows evolution to proceed.
Diese Kraft macht Evolution erst möglich.
We know how these changes are brought about through genetic changes that are passed
Bestimmte genetische Veränderungen werden von den Eltern
onto the offspring from the parent that has allowed it to survive.
an die Nachkommen weitergegeben und ermöglichen das Überleben.
These are the three components of the subtle system.
Dies sind die drei Komponenten des feinstofflichen Systems:
On the left side, the passive side, the so-called Ida Nadi;
auf der linken Seite – die Ida Nadi –,
on the right side, the so-called sun channel, the active side or the Pingala Nadi;
auf der rechten Seite – die Pingala Nadi –,
and in the center, we have a power
und in der Mitte die Kraft,
that allows evolution but, evolution in a spiritual sense.
die spirituelle Evolution ermöglicht – die Sushumna Nadi.
The microcosm is reflected in the macrocosm, and now we come to the autonomic nervous system.
Der Mikrokosmos spiegelt sich im Makrokosmos.
The autonomic nervous system also has its two components.
Darum hat das autonome Nervensystem ebenfalls zwei Komponenten:
One is the sympathetic nervous system; the other is the parasympathetic nervous system.
das sympathische und das parasympathische Nervensystem.
The sympathetic nervous system governs your flight or fight responses.
Das sympathische Nervensystem steuert unsere Kampf- oder Fluchtreaktionen:
For example, a human being sees a danger,
In einer Gefahrensituation
either he or she wants to fight
will der Menschen entweder kämpfen
or to run away from it.
oder weglaufen.
That triggers your heart rate to either pump faster, maybe run away from the danger.
Das Herz schlägt schneller, um sich einer Gefahr zu entziehen.
So that's one.
Das wäre eine Möglichkeit.
The other is the evolutionary, or the parasympathetic nervous system.
Das andere ist das evolutionäre oder parasympathische Nervensystem.
The parasympathetic nervous system is your rest-and-digest system.
Es steuert unser Ruhe- und Verdauungssystem,
It allows the individual to repose, to relax, and to nourish.
erlaubt uns, zu entspannen und Nahrung zu verwerten.
The left and the right, the subtle systems,
Die linken und rechten feinstofflichen
or the sympathetic systems, are something that are energy-expending systems.
und sympathischen Systeme
They consume energy; they expend energy.
verbrauchen oder wenden Energie auf.
We either consume energy in our desires, by having desires,
Wir verbrauchen Energie durch Wünsche
or we consume energy bringing those desires into action.
und dadurch, dass wir sie in die Tat umsetzen.
The parasympathetic nervous system allows us to rest and to nourish ourselves,
Durch bisher ungeklärte biologische Mechanismen
and in that way, through mechanisms that we have not yet biologically elucidated,
ermöglicht es das parasympathische Nervensystem auch
allow us to evolve.
uns zu entwickeln.
I'll stop there.
Hier möchte ich zunächst anhalten.
I hope that that kind of answers the question, but I'm happy to take more questions
Hoffentlich habe ich die Frage beantwortet.
if that did not fully explain it.
Falls nicht, fahre ich gerne fort.
Thanks, Dr. Ashish, for that explanation. And as we continue to zoom
Danke, Dr. Pradhan, für diese Erklärungen.
into the subtle system, after having understood a bit about
Nachdem wir etwas von der Funktion
these energy channels or these Nadis, we would like to understand from you
dieser Nadis gehört haben,
a little bit about the plexus now.
wüssten wir gerne etwas über die Nervenzentren (Plexus).
So, how is a plexus formed?
Wie entsteht ein Plexus,
What role do plexuses play in the functioning of the human body?
und welche Rolle spielen diese Geflechte im menschlichen Körper?
Things of that nature, if you can explain to the audiences.
Können Sie das unseren Zuschauern erklären?
Sure.
Gerne.
So, a plexus is derived from the Latin word,
Das Wort ‘Plexus’ leitet sich aus dem Lateinischen ab
and it means a braid,
und bedeutet so viel wie ‘Geflecht’ –
like a braid of hair, for example, like women who have hair, longer hair,
wie etwa bei einem Haarzopf.
or even men or women, if you tie that in a braid, that's the word, that's the origin of it.
Das ist der Ursprung dieses Wortes.
That's how it looks.
So sieht es aus.
Why is it called a plexus?
Warum wird es Plexus genannt?
We saw last time that the central nervous system consists of the brain and the spinal cord,
Das zentrale Nervensystem besteht aus Gehirn und Rückenmark.
and through the spinal cord which passes through the vertebral column,
Das Rückenmark verläuft durch die Wirbelsäule
you have nerves that come out of the vertebra from the sides.
und seitlich treten Nerven aus den Wirbeln heraus.
When the nerves come out from the vertebra, they come together
Diese austretenden Nerven
from different parts, and the plexus is like, if you open the electrical box
laufen wie die Drähte in einem Sicherungskasten
in your house, you see a bunch of wires coming together.
aus verschiedenen Richtungen zusammen.
So, a plexus is like nature's way of organizing the nerves.
In einem Plexus organisiert die Natur also die Nerven.
The nerves that come out, and these nerves, as we know, go further out,
Sie treten aus, verlaufen weiter nach außen
and they enter the various organs of the body.
und treten in verschiedene Organe des Körpers ein.
So, whether it is the heart, whether it is the lungs,
Das kann das Herz, die Lunge
whether it is the stomach, the pancreas, the liver.
oder der Magen, die Bauchspeicheldrüse, die Leber
And also, of course, the skeletal musculature.
und natürlich auch die Skelettmuskulatur sein.
So, these nerves, when they come out, they bunch together,
Die austretenden Nerven bündeln sich,
they come together, and that is what is called a plexus.
und das nennt man einen Plexus.
A plexus is, from a Sahaj point of view,
Ein Plexus ist aus der Perspektive von Sahaja Yoga
the gross manifestation of what we call energy centers or chakras within the body.
die grobstoffliche Manifestation eines Energiezentrums oder ‘Chakras’.
The Yoga Sutras have described seven principal energy centers.
Die Yoga-Sutras beschreiben sieben Hauptenergiezentren.
There are multiple other centers as well, but there are seven energy centers
Es gibt noch zahlreiche andere, doch die Reihe der sieben Hauptzentren
that start from something that is below our vertebral column,
beginnt etwas unterhalb der Wirbelsäule
right up the way, right into the crown of our head.
und verläuft ganz nach oben bis zum Scheitel.
The hypothesis is that the energy center itself exists
Diese Energiezentren existieren ‘hypothetisch’
at a very, very subtle level within the human body.
auf einer feinstofflichen Ebene im menschlichen Körper.
The energy center, or the chakra, cannot actually be seen
Tatsächlich können diese Chakras
through any current means of diagnostic techniques,
mit den heutigen diagnostischen Verfahren
for example, MRI scans or functional MRI scans or CT scans.
wie MRT oder CT nicht sichtbar gemacht werden.
You cannot put something in and try to see it functionally,
Man kann nichts injizieren, um ihre Funktion zu erkennen,
nor can you dissect the body at a level where you see it,
noch den Körper auf einer Ebene sezieren, auf der man sie sieht.
because these energy centers function or exist at the plane of energy.
Diese Zentren funktionieren und existieren auf energetischer Ebene.
It is not a matter per se; it is energy.
Es ist keine Materie, sondern Energie.
And these energy centers, at specific parts of the human body,
Diese Chakras steuern die Nervenzentren (Plexus)
govern the functioning of these nerve centers we call plexuses.
bestimmter Köperregionen.
The energy flow is from the energy center to the plexus,
Die Energie fließt vom Chakra zum Plexus
and from the plexus, it goes through the nerves into the organs.
und vom Plexus durch die Nerven in die Organe.
That is how the energy center - the chakra - governs the functioning
So regulieren die Chakren die Körperfunktionen
of the human body in the autonomic nervous system.
über das autonome Nervensystem.
That’s essentially the schema.
Das ist das essenzielle Schema.
So, you have the energy center that has the energy
Das Chakra liefert also die ‘steuernde’ Energie.
that, quote-unquote, controls— I have to use hand quotes here—
Das Wort ‘steuern’ muss man in Gänsefüßchen setzen,
because there is no real neurotransmitter-y system, as we discussed last time.
denn es gibt kein echtes Neurotransmittersystem.
There is no acetylcholine, there is no adrenaline,
Es gibt kein Acetylcholin, Adrenalin,
there is no dopamine or serotonin that does it.
Dopamin oder Serotonin.
But through ways that we have not yet elucidated, but you can feel it through your awareness
Doch in der Praxis dieser Meditationsform, kann man spüren,
once you practice this form of meditation, that the energy flows
wie die Energie von den Chakren zu den Plexus und den Organen fließt,
from the energy center to the plexus, from the plexus to the organ,
auch wenn es bisher noch nicht erklärt werden kann.
and that is how the chakra, plexus, organ system functions to maintain, once again,
So arbeitet das Chakra-Plexus-Organ-System,
the balance in the body, the internal ecosystem of the body.
um das innere Gleichgewicht und Ökosystem des Körpers, aufrechtzuerhalten.
That is how the nadis and the chakras come together.
So arbeiten Nadis und Chakren zusammen.
It is very important to remember, as we go on our journey
Das ist sehr wichtig,
and we discuss this in future episodes, that we should avoid the trap
damit wir nicht, wie die moderne Medizin,
that modern medicine has fallen into, which is to look at individual components
von einzelnen Komponenten
and then try to make a sense of the whole.
auf das Ganze schließen.
To understand the human spiritual system or the subtle system, one needs to take, in fact,
Um das spirituelle oder feinstoffliche System zu verstehen,
the directly opposite approach, which is a holistic approach,
muss man einen ganzheitlichen Ansatz wählen
to start from understanding that the system functions in an integrated fashion,
und voraussetzen, dass es auf integrierte Weise funktioniert.
and to try to break it down
Das subtile System auf seine Komponenten herunterzubrechen,
into its components is a reductive approach.
ist ein reduktionistischer Ansatz.
But, at the same time, it does help to understand a little bit,
Doch gleichzeitig hilft er, es teilweise zu verstehen.
but that is how it functions.
Doch so funktioniert es.
So, even if one chakra controls, maybe in theory, one plexus,
Selbst wenn ein Chakra theoretisch einen Plexus kontrolliert,
in reality, it probably controls many, many more plexuses
steuert es in der Realität wahrscheinlich viele weitere
and functions in ways that are very complex, that human understanding still hasn't
und funktioniert so komplex, dass das menschliche Verständnis
been able to pattern.
es noch nicht nachvollziehen kann.
I will stop there.
Hier höre ich erst einmal auf und hoffe,
I hope that provides some perspective of why the plexus is so important to understand
die Bedeutung der Nervengeflechte vor dem Hintergrund
within the broader concept of human spirituality.
menschlicher Spiritualität, verständlich dargestellt zu haben.
Thanks, Dr. Ashish, for that understanding, because all along I always thought
Danke für diese Erklärungen, Dr. Pradhan.
that chakra, energy center, and plexus are all the same things,
Ich dachte, Chakras und Plexus wären dasselbe.
and I know we use these terms without knowing so much about them,
Wir verwenden diese Begriffe, ohne viel darüber zu wissen.
but thanks for explaining that.
Danke, dass Sie das verdeutlicht haben.
If you can talk to us
Könnten Sie jetzt etwas über die
about the hypothesis that underlies the relationship
‘hypothetische’ Beziehung zwischen Chakra und Plexus
between a chakra and a plexus, and why is it important for us to understand that?
und über ihre Bedeutung sagen?
Excellent.
Gerne.
So, the chakra is, from a Sahaj point of view,
Ein Chakra ist – aus der Perspektive Sahaja Yogas –
the seat of divine power.
der Sitz der göttlichen Kraft.
It expresses itself as pure love, and each of these energy centers, or chakras,
Es drückt sich als reine Liebe aus, und jedes Energiezentrum
manifest different qualities.
manifestiert verschiedene Qualitäten.
And it is through the energy center - that is, the chakra -
Das Chakra steuert durch seine,
that the energy transmitted to the plexus governs the functioning
an den Plexus übertragene Energie,
of that particular organ system or organs within the remit of that plexus.
die Organfunktionen in der Zuständigkeit dieses Plexus.
So, as we will see as we move along, there are specific plexuses
Es gibt also bestimmte Plexus,
that look after specific organs.
die sich um bestimmte Organe kümmern.
The reason why this is important
Dies ist von Bedeutung,
is to understand both the physiology and the pathology.
um die Physiologie und die Pathologie zu verstehen.
The physiology is very simple, as we just expressed.
Die Physiologie ist sehr einfach:
Energy transmitted to the plexus and therefore the functioning of the organ system.
Energie wird auf den Plexus und dann auf das Organsystem übertragen.
Equally important, if the energy center is overused,
Auch von Bedeutung ist es, ein Chakra zu überbeanspruchen.
there is a finite amount of energy
Die Energiemenge
that is present at each of the individual chakra levels
jedes Chakras
when an individual takes birth.
ist von Geburt an begrenzt.
And throughout our life, we keep on expending that energy that we are born with,
Im Laufe unseres Lebens verbrauchen wir die Energie, mit der wir geboren wurden –
unless and until you get into a state we call self-realization,
es sei denn, man erlangt die Selbst-Verwirklichung.
and then that energy can be replenished.
Dann kann diese Energie wieder aufgefüllt werden.
But for most individuals, from the time of their birth
Doch für die meisten Menschen steht zwischen Geburt und Tod
till they pass on, is a limited amount of energy.
nur eine begrenzte Energiemenge zur Verfügung.
If that energy is not used in a wise and an optimal manner,
Wird diese Energie nicht optimal genutzt,
then it places strain on that chakra.
belastet es die Chakras.
That strain is then reflected at the level of the plexus
Diese Belastung spiegelt sich auf der Plexusebene wider,
because there is an imbalance.
weil ein Ungleichgewicht entsteht.
The key to understanding everything is the balance of this ecosystem.
Der Schlüssel zum Verständnis all dessen, liegt im Gleichgewicht dieses Ökosystems
And if that plexus gets into a state of imbalance, quote-unquote.
und ob diese Plexus in ein Ungleichgewicht geraten.
Medicine doesn't easily explain this,
Die Medizin hat dafür keine einfache Erklärung.
but at the spiritual level, we can explain it
Doch durch unsere zunehmende Selbst-Wahrnehmung in Sahaja Yoga
through our growth in our self-awareness through Sahaj.
können wir es auf spiritueller Ebene erklären.
If the plexus gets imbalanced, then the organ systems it governs
Gerät ein Plexus aus dem Gleichgewicht,
get imbalanced as well.
folgen auch die von ihm gesteuerten Organsysteme.
Which - in other words - is what we mean by imbalance?
Was meinen wir mit ‘Ungleichgewicht‘?
Imbalance implies the beginning of a pathological state,
Ungleichgewicht bedeutet den Beginn eines pathologischen Zustands.
which may or may not be easily detectable, but it starts at a very subtle level,
Vielleicht ist er nicht sofort nachweisbar, aber er beginnt auf der subtilen Ebene
and then over a period of time, it manifests as gross pathology.
und manifestiert sich im Laufe der Zeit als grobstoffliche Pathologie.
And that is why it is important to understand the governance structure
Deshalb ist es wichtig, den Steuerungsmechanismus
from the energy center, that is the chakra, to the plexus, to the organ system.
vom Chakra, zum Plexus und zum Organsystem zu verstehen.
Doctor, from what you mentioned, it seems like there has to be a wise use
Doktor, demnach muss es eine weise Nutzung
of the finite energy that we are born with.
der endlichen Energie geben, mit der wir geboren werden.
If you can help us understand what does it mean to use that energy wisely
Wie nutzen wir diese Energie weise,
or discreetly so that we don't get our chakras out of balance?
um unsere Chakren nicht aus dem Gleichgewicht bringen?
Let's take an example of a heart chakra,
Nehmen wir das Herz-Chakra:
the one that governs the cardiac plexus and our cardiovascular system,
Es steuert den Herzplexus und unser Herz-Kreislauf-System,
but basically the cardiac system.
aber im Grunde das Herzsystem.
For example, if we overwork, if we overstrain ourselves,
Vielleicht überarbeiten und überanstrengen wir uns,
we know that we are pursuing something, maybe it's a career opportunity,
weil wir beruflich aufsteigen wollen.
we want to work, and everybody wants to get ahead in life, and that's okay.
Wir wollen arbeiten und vorankommen – das ist in Ordnung.
The question is, is your ambition, is your drive putting you in a place
Doch Ehrgeiz und Tatendrang bringen uns vielleicht an einen Punkt,
where you can actually feel that you are under stress,
an dem wir uns gestresst fühlen
and that stress, at some point,
und dass sich dieser Stress
is manifesting in the form of essential hypertension.
als Bluthochdruck manifestiert.
Your systolic is going up, your diastolic is going up,
Unser systolischer und diastolischer Wert steigt.
at a certain age or whatever the case may be; then knowingly doing it,
Daher mag es ab einem bestimmten Alter oder aus anderen Gründen unklug sein,
or continuing to do it, is being unwise about it,
wissentlich damit weiter zu machen – denn jetzt sollten wir es wissen.
because now we should know. Most people don't have knowledge
Die meisten Menschen wissen nichts von Chakren.
about the chakras, but they do understand blood pressure or hypertension—
Doch sie verstehen Bluthochdruck.
because, potentially, it's a silent thing. But if you get the symptoms,
Potenziell ist es eine stille Sache. Doch manifestieren sich die Symptome
and if you are diagnosed with it, that's different.
und wird er diagnostiziert, dann ist es etwas anderes.
So, this is what we mean by being wise about it: that whatever your drives in life,
Das meinen wir mit ‘weise sein’: Was auch immer uns antreibt,
whatever your desires, wisdom, which is, again, an innate quality
was auch immer wir uns wünschen –
that comes to us from the first energy center, which we shall be talking about shortly,
Weisheit ist eine angeborene Qualität unseres ersten Energiezentrums.
needs to manifest itself in both our desires as well as our actions,
Sie muss sich in unseren Wünschen und Handlungen manifestieren,
because otherwise the system goes out of that.
denn sonst gerät das System aus den Fugen.
The energy center for that particular organ, or for that particular system,
Das Energiezentrum für dieses bestimmte Organ oder System
can start manifesting in ways that we now describe as, maybe, diseases
kann sich als Krankheit
or disorders of the human body.
oder Störungen manifestieren.
It is said that we often lead our lives in ignorance and, unknowingly or knowingly,
Man sagt, dass wir aus Unwissenheit bewusst oder unbewusst
put so much demand on our energy centers to the extent that we are creating
hohe Anforderungen an unsere Energiezentren stellen.
pathological conditions for us, like you explained.
Dadurch erzeugen wir pathologische Zustände.
Doctor, we'd like to understand if modern medicine historically has studied
Versuchte die moderne Medizin – historisch gesehen –,
or tried to study any connection between the autonomic nervous system
eine Verbindung zwischen dem autonomen Nervensystem
and the subtle system.
und dem subtilen System herzustellen?
That's a great question, Monikaji.
Das ist eine wichtige Frage, Monika.
Modern medicine has not really tried,
Die moderne Medizin versucht es nicht wirklich.
though if we look at the Hippocratic tradition,
Zur Zeit des Hippokrates
it certainly tried in the past, particularly during the time of Hippocrates, to make that linkage.
war es jedoch anders.
For example, Hippocrates was known to use methods that would bring the systems into balance.
Hippokrates war dafür bekannt, Systeme ins Gleichgewicht zu bringen.
But Galen, who succeeded Hippocrates for about 1500 years,
Galen versuchte 1.500 Jahre nach Hippokrates
his theory of humors (H-U-M-O-R, as in humours),
– ähnlich wie das subtile System –,
looked at trying to balance out the systems
mit seiner Vier-Säfte-Lehre,
between hot and cold,
ihre Qualitäten zwischen heiß und kalt auszugleichen
like the subtle system does, and then look at it from that point of view.
und es aus dieser Perspektive zu betrachten.
So, medicine had some, maybe in the distant past,
So besaß die Medizin vielleicht in ferner Vergangenheit
an understanding of the need to balance these elements within us.
ein Verständnis für eine Balance der Elemente in uns.
So, that was one, and Galen's theory of humours dominated medicine till about the Renaissance
Galens Säftelehre dominierte die Medizin etwa bis zur Renaissance,
and the arrival of the scientific method, the dissection of the human body,
dem Aufkommen der wissenschaftlichen Methodik und der Sezierung des menschlichen Körpers
the understanding of physiologic mechanisms, and then we lost it.
sowie dem Verständnis physiologischer Mechanismen. Dann ging sie verloren.
So, modern medicine doesn't really investigate it that much.
Die moderne Medizin kümmert sich also nicht wirklich darum.
In Ayurveda, it's probably become closest to bridging that gap
Die Ayurveda schließt wahrscheinlich am ehesten
between the subtle system and the autonomic nervous system,
die Lücke zwischen dem subtilen System und dem autonomen Nervensystem –
particularly through the tridosha theory, which is the kapha-pitta-vata theory,
besonders durch die Tridosha- oder Kapha-Pitta-Vata-Lehre.
which looks at the body as a composition of five elements:
Sie betrachtet den Körper zusammengesetzt aus den fünf Elementen:
earth, fire, water, ether, and air.
Erde, Feuer, Wasser, Äther und Luft.
So, it is through the tridosha theory— this tripartite theory—
Durch die Lehre der drei Doshas versuchen wir,
that we try to understand the relationship between the subtle system and the gross system,
die Beziehung zwischen dem subtilen und grobstofflichen System zu verstehen
and Ayurveda tries to use these elements to bring the body to a state of balance.
und mithilfe dieser Elemente, den Körper ins Gleichgewicht zu bringen.
But that's as far as medical systems go.
Doch das ist die Grenze, bis zu der diese medizinischen Systeme gehen.
There are other systems of medicine; the Chinese system tries to balance
Das chinesische System etwa,
the yin and yang part of it.
versucht, Yin und Yang auszugleichen.
So, medicine historically has had an understanding of it,
Die Medizin hatte also ein historisches Verständnis dafür,
but not to the extent that Sahaj can provide.
aber nicht in dem Maße, wie es Sahaja Yoga bieten kann.
Now that we understand that there are these energy centers,
Da wir jetzt wissen, dass es diese Energiezentren gibt,
let's begin by talking about the very first energy center.
lassen Sie uns über das erste Energiezentrum sprechen.
Could we understand a little bit about this and its role in human evolution
Welche Rolle spielt es in der menschlichen Evolution
as well as in spirituality?
und der Spiritualität?
The first energy center is, it would not be an overstatement to say,
Ohne zu übertreiben, ist das erste Energiezentrum
hypercritical to understand it, because it truly is the beginning of it all.
von großer Bedeutung. Es steht wirklich am Anfang von allem.
It is called the Muladhara chakra.
Es wird als ‘Muladhara Chakra’ bezeichnet
It sits outside of the vertebral column, just below it.
und sitzt außerhalb und direkt unter der Wirbelsäule.
It exists at an extremely subtle level.
Es existiert auf einer extrem feinstofflichen Ebene.
As we said, there is no way to see these energy centers,
Bis jetzt können wir diese Energiezentren noch nicht sehen.
but we can perceive them.
Doch wir können sie wahrnehmen.
So that chakra, Muladhara, essentially means the primordial support.
‘Muladhara’ bedeutet im Wesentlichen ‘ursprüngliche Stütze’.
It really is the fulcrum of everything.
Es ist wirklich der Angelpunkt von allem.
Before we start to understand the Muladhara chakra,
Bevor wir zum Muladhara Chakra kommen,
maybe just a step back into basic physics or quantum mechanics,
betrachten wir einige Grundlagen der Physik,
or quantum field theory.
der Quantenmechanik oder Quantenfeldtheorie.
Why is that important?
Warum ist das wichtig?
It's very important because, if you remember, in 2012, the CERN particle collider
2012 wies der CERN-Teilchenbeschleuniger
found the Higgs boson particle.
das Higgs-Boson nach.
Why was that important?
Warum wurde der Nobelpreis an Personen verliehen,
Why was the Nobel Prize awarded to the individuals who had, 40 years ago,
die vor 40 Jahren
propounded that theory?
diese Theorie aufstellten?
And the reason is the existence of the Higgs field,
Der Grund ist die Existenz des Higgs-Feldes,
which is supposed to permeate all known universes.
das angeblich alle bekannten Universen durchdringt.
And what the Higgs boson proved was that energy somehow imparts properties
Das Higgs-Boson beweist, dass reine Energie
to electromagnetic particles, or at that quantum level,
elektromagnetischen Teilchen Eigenschaften verleiht
in that quantum state, that gives them mass.
oder ihnen auf der Quantenebene eine Masse gibt.
Mass, in turn, produces gravity.
Masse wiederum erzeugt Schwerkraft.
What is gravity?
Was ist Schwerkraft?
It's the curvature of space-time.
Schwerkraft ist die Krümmung der Raumzeit.
So, whatever mass you have, it leads to that part of gravity,
Welche Masse man auch hat, sie erzeugt ein
and that is a constant.
im Verhältnis immer gleiches Maß an Schwerkraft.
Newton showed us that there is a constant in terms of gravity.
Newton zeigte, dass es in der Schwerkraft eine Konstante gibt.
Why is that important?
Warum ist das wichtig?
This is important to know that energy preceded the creation of matter,
Es zeigt, dass Energie der Erschaffung von Materie vorausging.
and that helps us to understand our subtle system and also our chakras.
Das hilft, unser subtiles System und unsere Chakren zu verstehen.
The Muladhara chakra, or the first energy center, represents
Das Muladhara Chakra repräsentiert als erstes Energiezentrum
that first primordial step after the Big Bang, or around that time, or just following that,
den ersten uranfänglichen Schritt nach dem der Urknall einsetzte
as this heat was released, and then that heat started slowly,
und seine ursprüngliche Hitze
as the system started coalescing,
allmählich nachließ und sich seine Energie
leading to the formation of the big stars. And within the cores of these big stars,
zu großen Sternen verdichtete. In den Kernen dieser Sterne
you had fusion reactions where hydrogen and helium nuclei
begannen Fusionsreaktionen aus Wasserstoff- und Heliumkernen,
started coming together, and elements were formed.
höhere chemische Elemente aufzubauen.
And a key element was carbon.
Ein Schlüsselelement war
And carbon, as we know, is tetravalent.
der vierwertige Kohlenstoff.
It has four valencies, and it is the basic molecule
Er hat vier Valenzen und ist das Basismolekül,
that leads to formation of organic compounds.
das zur Bildung organischer Verbindungen führt.
And the human being, or everything that we see around us,
Der Mensch und alles Lebendige um uns herum
animals, plants, whatever,
– Tiere, Pflanzen usw. –
is a product of that organic chemistry.
ist ein Produkt dieser organischen Chemie.
So this element, carbon, which has four valencies,
Der Kohlenstoff kann interessanterweise
is also interestingly represented in some ways as the swastika,
auch als ‘Swastika’ dargestellt werden,
which is a very traditional ancient symbol.
als sehr traditionelles und uraltes Symbol.
Unfortunately, in the last century, it got a very bad reputation,
Leider erhielt es im letzten Jahrhundert einen schlechten Ruf.
but it has nothing to do with it.
Doch das hat keine Bedeutung.
It has been recognized as a symbol of auspiciousness and purity
Es ist das Symbol für Gottgefälligkeit, Reinheit und alles,
and everything that goes with it.
was damit einhergeht.
So, that is how it starts.
So fängt es an.
So, this is the Muladhara chakra.
Das Muladhara Chakra
The Muladhara chakra is the fulcrum, literally the support of the entire system,
ist der Angelpunkt und die Stütze des gesamten Systems.
and it is governed by an aspect of divinity whose manifestation is primordial innocence.
Es wird vom göttlichen Aspekt ursprünglicher Unschuld regiert.
So, once again, to recap, you have energy,
Es gibt also eine Ur-Energie,
that is the primordial energy that somehow imparted its properties
die ihr Potenzial irgendwie auf elektromagnetische Teilchen übertragen hat.
to electromagnetic particles that created mass, and that mass led to gravity.
Diese Teilchen erzeugten Masse, und diese wiederum Schwerkraft.
And without gravity, we would not have existed,
Ohne Schwerkraft würden wir nicht existieren,
because otherwise we would have just been,
sondern wären nur Elektronen,
like electrons spinning forever at the speed of light.
die für immer mit Lichtgeschwindigkeit umherkreisten.
And that gravity is also kept at a very specific constant,
Die Schwerkraft wiederum wird konstant gehalten;
because if that constant were to be a little less or a little more
denn wäre sie größer,
we would have just collapsed together into
kollabierten wir zu einer hyperdichten Materie,
a hyperdense kind of matter that would be impossible to define;
die unmöglich zu definieren wäre.
or if it had been less, we would have just been flying into space.
Wäre sie geringer, schwebten wir einfach in den Weltraum davon.
Muladhara chakra is very important because it represents that primordial purity
Das Muladhara Chakra repräsentiert die ursprüngliche Reinheit der Kraft,
of the power that created us, and at a gross level, it is represented
die uns erschuf und manifestiert sich auf grobstofflicher Ebene
by the pelvic plexus.
als Beckenplexus (Plexus pelvicus).
The pelvic plexus is formed by nerves that come out of the sacrum bone
Dieser Plexus wird von den Nerven gebildet, die aus dem Kreuzbein
and as well as the last parts of the lumbar vertebra.
und den letzten Teilen der Lendenwirbelsäule austreten.
They come together, they exist on both sides, and the pelvic plexus innervates
Sie treffen zusammen und existieren auf beiden Seiten.
the excretory organs as well as the reproductive organs
Der Beckenplexus innerviert die Ausscheidungs- und Fortpflanzungsorgane
in the human body, in males as well as females,
des menschlichen Körpers bei Männern und Frauen,
as shown in the animation.
wie in der Animation.
For example, the uterus or the urinary bladder,
Er kontrolliert etwa die Gebärmutter, die Harnblase
the excretory organs, those are the organs that are controlled —
und die Ausscheidungsorgane.
again, the word 'control' is used in a spiritual sense, not just in a physical sense —
Das Wort ‘kontrolliert’ wird wieder im spirituellen
by the pelvic plexus.
und nicht nur im physischen Sinne verwendet.
The pelvic plexus—there are two of them on either side of the vertebral column
Es gibt zwei Beckenplexus auf beiden Seiten der Wirbelsäule
at the lower part of the body (the lower pelvis). That's why it's called the pelvic plexus,
im unteren Teil des Körpers, dem unteren Becken.
and that's how they control these organs.
So steuern beide Plexus diese Organe.
But the power that controls the plexuses is represented by the Muladhara chakra.
Doch die Kraft, die die Plexus kontrolliert, stellt das Muladhara Chakra zur Verfügung.
Before we end this question, to re-emphasize what we said
Um es nochmals zu betonen:
in answer to a previous question, the Muladhara chakra should not be
das Muladhara Chakra sollte nicht
looked at in a unitary fashion; it is to be seen as part of an integral system
isoliert betrachtet werden; es ist Teil des integrierten Systems,
that literally sits above it, but the Muladhara chakra provides
das darüber angeordnet ist. Das Muladhara Chakra ist seine Stütze.
the support to it all, and its main function is to provide gravity,
Seine Hauptfunktion besteht darin, Schwerkraft zu liefern.
and through that gravity, it allows the support of the entire system.
Sie wiederum ermöglicht die Unterstützung des gesamten Systems.
It is an extraordinarily important energy center to be aware of.
Es ist ein außerordentlich wichtiges Energiezentrum.
You mentioned two things: you mentioned the sacrum bone,
Sie erwähnten das Kreuzbein.
and we'd like to understand why it is considered relevant in this context.
Warum ist es in diesem Kontext relevant?
You also mentioned primordial energy. Is this the same as the Kundalini energy
Sie erwähnten auch die Ur-Energie. Ist das dieselbe wie die Kundalini-Energie?
that we hear about, and what is this Kundalini energy,
Was ist diese Kundalini?
and what role does it play in human spirituality?
Welche Rolle spielt sie in der menschlichen Spiritualität?
That is indeed true.
Das ist wahr.
Once again, as we look at the graphics, we look at the animation,
Die Grafiken und die Animation zeigen
we see that at the bottom of the vertebral column
am unteren Ende der Wirbelsäule
is a triangular bone called the os sacrum.
einen dreieckigen Knochen namens Os sacrum.
The Greeks realized that this was a very sacred place,
Die Griechen erkannten ihn als heilig.
and there is no reason to know so far, as far as we know,
Bisher wissen wir nicht,
why they would call it that particular bone.
warum sie ihn besonders hervorhoben.
There are theories about it; it is said that that is amongst the last bones
Es heißt, er gehöre zu den letzten Knochen, die zerfallen,
to be destroyed in the human body if a body is interred or is buried.
wenn ein Körper bestattet oder begraben wird.
It is an extremely strong bone; it looks like the hood of a snake,
Es ist ein sehr starker Knochen und sieht aus wie das Nackenschild einer Kobra.
and within this os sacrum, and this is why we believe in human spirituality,
In diesem Os sacrum – und deshalb glauben wir an eine menschliche Spiritualität –
resides the primordial energy in three and a half coils,
wohnt die Ur-Energie in dreieinhalb spiralförmigen
in the serpentine coils, and that energy is referred to in the yoga sutras
oder schlangenartigen Windungen. Diese Energie wird in den Yoga-Sutras
or in classical Sanskrit texts as Kundalini.
oder klassischen Sanskrit-Texten als ‘Kundalini’ bezeichnet.
Kundala means coiled and it sits there in three and a half coils.
‘Kundala’ bedeutet ‘gewunden’.
Other texts refer to it as the serpent power,
Andere Texte bezeichnen sie als die ‘Schlangenkraft’
or that power that resides within us.
oder einfach als ‘jene Kraft, die in uns wohnt’.
It is very interesting that ancient Greeks used to worship a god called Asclepius,
Die alten Griechen verehrten einen Gott namens Asklepios.
and Asclepius was known to cure diseases with the use of serpent power.
Er heilte Krankheiten mithilfe von Schlangenkraft.
So, even now, if you look at the most visible symbol of most physicians
Selbst heute zeigt das Symbol vieler Ärzte oder Mediziner
or medical societies you see a staff, and you see two serpents coiled around it,
einen Stab und zwei Schlangen, die sich darum winden.
and that comes from the legend of Asclepius, who was believed to cure diseases
Das leitet sich von der Asklepios-Legende ab, nach der er Krankheiten
using serpent power.
mithilfe von Schlangenkraft geheilt haben soll.
So, this is this energy that resides within us; this is the energy that allows us
Diese uns innewohnende Energie hebt unser Bewusstsein
to raise our consciousness from a human level to a level whereby we can perceive
von der menschlichen auf eine Ebene,
this existential reality that is absolute,
der existenziellen und absoluten Realität,
that we referred to in one of our previous episodes.
wie bereits früher erwähnt.
The sympathetic nervous system has nerves
Die Nerven des sympathischen Systems
that permeate each part of our body, including our nerves,
durchdringen jeden Teil unseres Körpers.
and when this energy is awakened within us, as it rises through the other energy centers,
Wird die Kundalini-Energie in uns erweckt,
which we will talk about in subsequent episodes,
steigt sie durch die höheren Energiezentren auf.
and it arrives and it pierces through the limbic system,
Zum Schluss durchdringt sie das limbische System
the fontanel area in that part of the brain, it allows us to feel that energy around us
im Fontanellenbereich des Gehirns. Dann spüren wir die Energie um uns herum,
that we otherwise cannot at a sensory level, and that is very important.
die wir sonst nicht hätten wahrnehmen können.
Biologically, it's interesting that it may not be
Die Kundalini-Energie an sich,
the Kundalini energy per se, but the Kundalini energy —
ermöglicht die Evolution
the fact that it allows an evolution — bears an interesting parallel
und weist eine interessante Parallele
to the double helical structure of the DNA molecule.
zur Doppelhelix-Struktur des DNS-Moleküls auf.
The DNA molecule, which exists within every cell and is the fundamental unit
Die DNS jeder Körperzelle ist die Grundeinheit
of all living organisms in every cell, consists of two strands
aller lebenden Organismen und besteht aus zwei Strängen,
that spiral around each other.
die sich umeinander winden.
One goes up, one goes down, and it contains the genetic code within itself,
In dieser Struktur ist ihr genetischer Code gespeichert.
and the reason why, as the founder of Sahaja, Shri Mataji, once explained, it is helical
Die Gründerin von Sahaja Yoga, Shri Mataji, erklärte einmal,
is because a helical movement allows you, if you move it, to arrive at a higher plane.
dass eine spiralförmige Bewegung es erlaubt, auf eine höhere Ebene zu gelangen.
Circular movement allows you to only come back to the starting point,
Eine kreisförmige Bewegung dagegen,
but a helical movement allows you to rise up.
bringt einen nur zum Ausgangspunkt zurück.
That's why you have a spiral staircase.
Deshalb gibt es Wendeltreppen.
So, in a kind of analogous fashion, the Kundalini energy allows us,
Genauso erhebt die Kundalini-Energie unser Bewusstsein
when it uncoils and as it rises, to raise our consciousness.
wenn sie sich entrollt und aufsteigt.
This is present in every human being, and it is also called the mother energy.
Sie in jedem Menschen vorhanden und wird auch als mütterliche Energie bezeichnet.
It is your individual mother because this is the energy that knows best
Sie ist unsere individuelle Mutter, weil sie die Energie ist, die weiß,
what is good for you, what is best for you. And it is a female energy
was das Beste für uns ist. Es ist eine weibliche Energie,
that resides within each one of us, dormant in the sacrum.
die in jedem von uns im Kreuzbein ruht.
And it is the awakening of this energy
Das Erwachen dieser Energie,
which is the ultimate object of all yoga practices.
ist das oberste Ziel aller Yoga-Praktiken.
In fact, yoga is defined as the awakening of this energy and its piercing
Tatsächlich beschreibt ‘Yoga’ das Erwecken dieser inneren Energie, ihr Durchdringen der Fontanelle
through the fontanel area, and the awakening of the limbic system.
und das damit verbundene Erwachen des limbischen Systems.
So, that's the Kundalini energy, which resides in the sacrum,
Die Kundalini-Energie wohnt im Kreuzbein,
and which certain systems of medicine, particularly in the past, were kind of aware of.
und einige medizinische Systeme der Vergangenheit waren sich ihrer irgendwie bewusst.
But it is extraordinarily challenging to awaken that energy,
Doch es ist sehr herausfordernd, diese Energie zu erwecken,
to make it uncoil itself and rise through the Sushumna Nadi,
sie dazu zu bringen, sich zu entrollen und durch die Sushumna Nadi aufzusteigen,
which, at a gross level,
die auf grobstofflicher Ebene
is represented by the parasympathetic nervous system.
durch das parasympathische Nervensystem repräsentiert wird.
So, you mentioned every human being has this energy,
Sie erwähnten, dass jeder Mensch diese Energie habe
and you also mentioned that this energy helps us raise our consciousness.
und dass diese Energie uns helfe, unser Bewusstsein zu erheben.
So, I guess my question is then, why does every human being not evolve
Warum entwickelt sich nicht jeder Mensch
up to a certain level of consciousness?
bis zu einem bestimmten Bewusstseinsgrad?
Why is that different?
Warum ist das so verschieden?
That's again a wonderful question.
Das ist wieder eine wunderbare Frage.
The reason is that this energy is a power that can be awakened, or is awakened,
Diese Energie ist eine Kraft, die nur durch die Gnade eines Meisters
only through the grace of a master. And unless and until there is a master
erweckt werden kann; und solange es keinen Meister gibt,
who has the, quote-unquote, authority or the ability to awaken it,
der die ‘Autorität’ oder die Fähigkeit hat, sie zu erwecken,
this energy does not rise.
steigt diese Energie nicht auf.
This energy, let's just say, has a mind of its own;
Diese Energie hat ihren eigenen Willen.
that is because it is of divine origin.
Sie ist göttlichen Ursprungs.
It is divinity personified within a human being,
Sie ist individualisierte Göttlichkeit im Menschen.
and that cannot be raised; that cannot come up;
Sie kann nicht gehoben werden und nicht aufsteigen, sie entrollt
it doesn't uncoil itself and start rising just because somebody wants it to be so.
und erhebt sich nicht, nur, weil es jemand verlangt.
It has to happen, or it can only happen, if that individual, that said individual,
Es muss oder kann nur geschehen, wenn das Individuum
comes in contact with a person who is a master and whose own energy is awakened to a state
einen Meister trifft, dessen eigene Energie diesen Zustand erreicht hat.
that can then allow for that other individual, who doesn't have it awakened,
Dann kann er die Kundalini
to be able to be awakened.
dieses Individuums erwecken.
We call it having a guru.
Wir nennen es ‘einen Guru haben’.
It's a kind of traditional way of saying it, but it is only through the grace of the guru—
Es ist eine traditionelle Ausdrucksweise. Doch nur durch die Gnade
of a true guru, a primordial, a person who is truly a true master,
eines wahren Gurus,
who has nothing but pure benevolence in his or her heart towards this other individual
der im Herzen nichts als reines Wohlwollen seinem Gegenüber hegt,
can facilitate the awakening of this inner energy,
wird die Erweckung dieser inneren Energie möglich.
which is very, very relatively straightforward in Sahaj,
In Sahaja Yoga ist das relativ einfach.
but that experience we can have after this session,
Doch diese Erfahrung können wir später in einer
as the session that is led by Shri Mataji herself.
von Shri Mataji persönlich geleiteten Meditation machen.
That's what I was going to say.
Das wollte ich gerade sagen.
I think it is, on that note, perfect time for our audiences
Das scheint der perfekte Zeitpunkt für unser Publikum zu sein,
to have that experience and then, just follow the instructions that the founder has,
diese Erfahrung zu machen und einfach den Anweisungen der Gründerin zu folgen.
because, like you mentioned, there has to be some expert or guru
Wie Sie sagen, muss es einen Experten oder Guru geben,
who has to be able to do this for you. And I would like to thank you, Dr. Ashish,
der dies für uns tun kann. Ich bedanke mich für Ihre heutige Zeit, Dr. Pradhan,
for your time today, and we look forward to talking to you again
und wir freuen uns, demnächst mit Ihnen
on the next energy center in our subtle system,
über das zweite Energiezentrum unseres subtilen Systems zu sprechen.
but thanks again for your time today.
Nochmals danke für Ihre Zeit heute.
Thank you very much.
Vielen Dank.
Great questions.
Tolle Fragen.
Enjoyed it.
Es war mir eine Freude.
Thank you.
Danke.
I hope everybody enjoys the meditation session as well.
Ich hoffe, alle werden die Meditation genießen.
Yes, we do hope that.
Ja, das hoffen wir sehr.
Shri Mataji: Called as the Muladhara chakra, which manifests the pelvic plexus outside.
Shri Mataji: Das Muladhara Chakra manifestiert sich äußerlich als Beckenplexus.
Now, this center is placed below the Kundalini, which is placed in the sacrum bone.
Es liegt unterhalb der Kundalini im Kreuzbein (Os sacrum).
This is called sacrum because it is a sacred bone.
‘Sacrum’ bedeutet ‘heilig’; man nannte diesen Knochen so, weil es ein heiliger ist.
In this bone lies the Kundalini, the residual power of our germination.
In ihm ruht die Kundalini – die residuelle Kraft unserer Keimung.
During the process of Kundalini awakening, you can see the pulsation down here.
Während der Erweckung der Kundalini könnt ihr sie hier unten pulsieren sehen.
You can also, through a stethoscope, see the rising of the Kundalini,
Man kann sie auch mit einem Stethoskop beim Aufsteigen verfolgen
and you can see the pulsation in the backbone till it reaches here in the fontanel bone area,
und in der Wirbelsäule pulsieren sehen – bis sie die Fontanelle erreicht
where it breaks through.
und durchbricht.
At that point, you do not feel any pulsation.
Dann spürt man sie nicht mehr Pulsieren,
As soon as this happens, from your hands, a cool breeze starts to flow.
sondern eine kühle Brise, beginnt aus euren Händen zu strömen.
You can feel it on your fingers, as shown here.
Ihr könnt sie auf euren Fingern spüren, wie hier gezeigt.
These are the terminal points of the sympathetic nervous system within us.
Dies sind die Endpunkte des sympathischen Nervensystems.
These represent all the centers that are inside us,
Sie repräsentieren alle Zentren in uns,
and you start feeling them on your fingers as absolutely your own experience.
und ihr spürt sie an euren Fingern als ureigene Erfahrung.
Keep your eyes closed.
Haltet eure Augen geschlossen.
First of all, please put your right hand on your heart.
Legt bitte die rechte Hand auf euer Herz.
All the time the left hand is towards Me.
Die linke Hand ist während der ganzen Zeit zu mir gerichtet.
Now, here you have to say in your heart, with all sincerity, Mother, am I the Spirit?
Fragt in eurem Herzen mit aller Aufrichtigkeit: Mutter, bin ich der Geist?"
Ask the question three times in your heart.
Stellt diese Frage dreimal in eurem Herzen.
This is a very fundamental question.
Das ist eine sehr grundlegende Frage.
Now bring the right hand on to the left hand side of your stomach,
Bringt nun die rechte Hand auf die linke Seite des Bauches,
in the upper part.
im oberen Teil ...
Here press it.
... und drückt hier auf den Bauch.
Now this is the center of your mastery, your guidance, your guru Tattva, as they say.
Dies ist das Zentrum eurer Meisterschaft, eurer Führung und eures ‘Guru-Tattvas’.
So ask a question, Mother, am I my own master?
Fragt also: "Mutter, bin ich mein eigener Meister?
This is the question to be asked three times.
Stellt diese Frage dreimal.
Mother, am I my own master?
"Mutter, bin ich mein eigener Meister?
Now bring your right hand down below in the lower part of the abdomen.
Legt nun eure rechte Hand nach unten auf den unteren Teil des Bauches.
Now this is the center from which all the Divine work is done,
Dies ist das Zentrum, durch das alle göttliche Arbeit,
all the pure work is done.
alle reine Arbeit getan wird.
So to ask six times, because this center has got six petals,
Hier bittet ihr sechsmal  – denn dieses Zentrum hat sechs Blütenblätter:
Mother, please give me pure knowledge.
"Mutter, bitte schenke mir reines Wissen.
Six times you just ask.
Bittet sechsmal darum.
As a result of this asking the Kundalini starts getting awakened.
Als Antwort auf diese Fragen, beginnt die Kundalini zu erwachen.
Now to help the Kundalini to rise you have to cooperate with Her.
Um der Kundalini beim Aufsteigen zu helfen, müsst ihr mit ihr kooperieren.
So please put your right hand on the left hand side
Legt also bitte die rechte Hand auf der linken Seite,
in the upper part of your abdomen and press it on the stomach.
zurück auf den oberen Teil des Bauches, und drückt dort wieder etwas auf diese Stelle.
Now here you have to say with full confidence,
Hier müsst ihr nun voller Vertrauen
to help the Kundalini to rise, Mother, I am my own master.
der Kundalini beim Aufsteigen helfen und sagen: Mutter, ich bin mein eigener Meister."
This you have to say ten times.
Sagt es zehnmal.
These are the ten commandments which you have to say,
Das sind die zehn Gebote, die ihr sagen müsst:
that Mother, I am my own master.
"Mutter, ich bin mein eigener Meister",
Now, ten times with full confidence.
zehnmal und voller Vertrauen.
Now please raise your right hand to your heart.
Hebt nun eure rechte Hand zum Herzen,
Now here you have to say, again with full confidence,
und sagt wieder vertrauensvoll:
Mother, I am the Spirit.
"Mutter, ich bin der Geist.
This is the truth, you are the Spirit.
Das ist die Wahrheit. Ihr seid der Geist.
But you have to say with full confidence, Mother, I am the Spirit.
Doch sagt es voller Vertrauen: Mutter, ich bin der Geist."
This you have to say twelve times.
Sagt es zwölfmal.
Now one has to know that God Almighty is the ocean of love.
Nun muss man wissen, dass der Allmächtige Gott der Ozean der Liebe ist.
But above all He is the ocean of forgiveness.
Doch vor allem ist Er der Ozean der Vergebung.
So He forgives.
Also vergibt Er.
Whatever wrong you do He forgives.
Was auch immer ihr Falsches tut – Er vergibt.
So don't feel guilty and put your right hand across
Fühlt euch also nicht schuldig und legt eure rechte Hand
on the left hand side in the corner which is made by your neck and your shoulder.
quer über den Halsansatz der linken Schulter.
Now here you have to say again with full confidence,
Hier sagt ihr wieder voller Vertrauen und sechzehnmal:
sixteen times, Mother, I am not guilty.
"Mutter, ich bin nicht schuldig.
Please say it, Mother, I am not guilty.
Bitte sagt es: "Mutter, ich bin nicht schuldig",
Sixteen times.
sechzehnmal,
I am not guilty at all.
"Ich bin überhaupt nicht schuldig.
Please say it.
Bitte sagt es.
Now raise your hand across on your forehead and it's a very important center.
Legt nun eure Hand quer über die Stirn. Dies ist ein sehr wichtiges Zentrum.
Here you have to say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
Hier müsst ihr von Herzen sagen: Mutter, ich vergebe jedem."
Please say it from your heart.
Bitte sagt es von Herzen.
How many times is not the point.
Es ist nicht so wichtig, wie oft.
Mother, I forgive everyone.
"Mutter, ich vergebe jedem.
Now some would say that it's very difficult to forgive.
Manche sagen vielleicht, es sei sehr schwierig zu vergeben.
But it's a myth that we do not forgive or we forgive.
Doch das ist ein Mythos, denn ob wir vergeben oder nicht –
We do not do anything in both the cases.
wir tun in beiden Fällen nichts.
But if we don't forgive then we play into wrong hands.
Wenn wir jedoch nicht vergeben, spielen wir in falsche Hände.
So please say from your heart, Mother, I forgive everyone.
Also sagt bitte von Herzen: Mutter, ich vergebe jedem."
Now please take your hand on the back agnya, the same center, on the back side of your head
Legt eure Hand jetzt bitte auf das hintere "Agnya", dasselbe Zentrum auf der Rückseite des Kopfes.
and allow your head to rest on it and push it back a little bit.
Lasst den Kopf auf der Hand ruhen und legt ihn ein wenig zurück.
Now here you have to say for your satisfaction,
Hier sagt nun – zu eurer eigenen Zufriedenheit
because you always feel guilty, that, O Divine, if I have done anything wrong,
und weil ihr Euch oft schuldig fühlt –: Oh Göttliches, wenn ich etwas falsch gemacht habe,
please forgive me.
bitte vergib mir.
Please forgive me, from your heart.
"Bitte vergib mir" – sagt es von Herzen.
Stretch your hand fully and put your center of your palm
Streckt dann eure Hand vollständig aus und legt die Mitte der Handfläche
on top of the fontanel bone area, which was a very soft bone in your childhood.
oben auf den Bereich der Fontanelle, der in eurer Kindheit noch ein weicher Knochen war.
Press it hard.
Drückt ihn fest.
Press hard your scalp.
Drückt fest auf eure Kopfhaut.
Now you have to move it seven times saying one thing, which you have to ask for,
Bewegt sie nun siebenmal im Uhrzeigersinn und bittet:
Mother, please give us My Self-realization, because I cannot force on you.
"Mutter, bitte gib mir meine Selbst-Verwirklichung! Ich kann sie euch nicht aufzwingen –
So you have to ask for it.
darum müsst ihr darum bitten.
Seven times press it hard and move it seven times very hard.
Drückt die Kopfhaut fest, bewegt sie siebenmal fest im Uhrzeigersinn
Slowly saying that.
und sagt dabei langsam diese Worte.